<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Debugging | blog.byteb.us]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.byteb.us/blog/categories/debugging/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.byteb.us/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-16T11:22:34+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.byteb.us/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Marc Löhe]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Debugging Typo3 4.7 with Xdebug in PHPStorm]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.byteb.us/blog/2013/05/15/debugging-typo3-4-7-with-xdebug-in-phpstorm/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-15T23:17:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.byteb.us/blog/2013/05/15/debugging-typo3-4-7-with-xdebug-in-phpstorm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since I&rsquo;m currently working an Extbase-Extension for TYPO3 4.7, I had to debug some backend code. I didn&rsquo;t find anything on how to set this up with <a href="http://xdebug.org/">Xdebug</a> and <a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/phpstorm/">PHPStorm</a>, so I&rsquo;ll write it down here.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Requirements</h2>

<p>XDebug has to be installed and configured to work with PHPStorm, which works out fine with the <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/phpstorm/webhelp/configuring-xdebug.html">official docs</a>. I assume that Xdebug and PHPStorm are tested and working.</p>

<h2>Symlinks</h2>

<p>Typo3 4.7 can be installed as usual, but you want to physically put the <code>typo3_src</code> folder into your webroot instead of just symlinking to it. This caused quite some headache while setting it up.</p>

<p>The webroot folder should look like this regarding symlinks:</p>

<p><code>
webroot/
  typo3_src/
  t3lib &gt; typo3_src/t3lib/
  typo3 &gt; typo3_src/typo3/
  index.php &gt; typo3_src/index.php
</code></p>

<h2>PHPStorm setup</h2>

<h3>Directories</h3>

<p>When setting up the PHPStorm project you should choose your webroot folder as the <em>Content root</em> of your project. It would have been even better to select your plugin folder as <em>Content root</em> and only include the core sources, but there was no obvious way to get it done.</p>

<p>You can check this by opening the project settings in the Menu <em>Directories</em>.</p>

<h3>Path mappings</h3>

<p>In the symlink setup above, the folders <code>t3lib</code> and <code>typo3</code> as well as the <code>ìndex.php</code> were symlinked inside the <code>typo3_src</code> folder. We don&rsquo;t have to make a physical copy of them that way, but we have to tell PHPStorm about it.</p>

<p>You can do this in the project settings, look for the submenu <em>Servers</em> inside <em>PHP</em>. You will have to setup a server now if you haven&rsquo;t already. Activate the &ldquo;Use path mappings&rdquo; option. For each path in your project, you can now specify it&rsquo;s absolute path by filling the column in the mappings table. Specify the absolute path inside <code>typo3_src</code> for the two symlinked directories and the symlinked <code>index.php</code>.</p>

<p>Set up theses mappings:</p>

<h2>```</h2>

<h2>Project path > Absolute path on the server</h2>

<p>/path/to/webroot > /path/to/webroot
  t3lib > /path/to/webroot/typo3_src/t3lib
  typo3 > /path/to/webroot/typo3_src/typo
  index.php > /path/to/webroot/typo3_src/index.php
```</p>

<p>Notice that the path for the webroot was mapped to it&rsquo;s own path. While testing this seemed to be necessary.</p>

<h3>One more mapping</h3>

<p>Also check the URL mapping by navigating to <em>Deployment</em> in your project settings. You will have to create a deployment server configuration if you haven&rsquo;t already. Make sure, that you have a mapping for your webroot by entering your webroot&rsquo;s path into the <code>Local path</code> field and <code>/</code> into the <code>Web path on server: xyz</code> field.</p>

<h2>That&rsquo;s it!</h2>

<p>The setup isn&rsquo;t too complicated, but there are enough possibilities to make something wrong, which I apparently did in almost all cases.</p>

<p>You can use <a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/phpstorm/marklets/">bookmarklets</a> and breakpoints to quickly debug your code on the fly. If you are not sure where to start, look for the <code>webroot/index.php</code> for the frontend and <code>webroot/typo3/index.php</code> to get you started. Also have a look at the <em>Network</em> tab of your devtools: a lot of requests are initiated on other endpoints like <code>webroot/typo3/alt_doc.php</code> or <code>webroot/typo3/mod.php</code> and a lot of others.</p>

<p>Also stay aware of the fact that the TYPO3 backend is made up of nested iFrames (which is slightly awkward&hellip;). If you want to reinitiate a request, it is probably better to right click into the concerned area and choose <em>Reload frame</em> than reloading the whole page which leaves you with the dashboard.</p>

<p>After writing down all of this I have to add one more thing: debugging software really is the most effective way to effectively learn, what it does. So yes, it is worth all the hassle of setting it up.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
